const e=JSON.parse('[{"question":"Which of the following is true with regard to the association between schizophrenia and recorded crime rates?","options":{"A":"The risk is increased for non-violent crimes only","B":"The risk is increased for violent but not non-violent crimes","C":"The risk of crime is increased for narrow diagnosis of schizophrenia rather than broad diagnosis of psychosis","D":"The association is seen only for less serious violent acts","E":"The risk is highest for violent crimes for both narrowly defined schizophrenia and broadly defined psychosis"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Various types of studies have been hitherto employed to study the association between recorded crime and psychosis. One must remember that officially recorded crime may only be the tip of the proverbial iceberg in such studies. Various regional policies, jurisdictions, and practices affect the rate of recorded crime; in any case, these rates are not a true reflection of violence in society. Many such studies have consistently found that a narrow diagnosis of schizophrenia or much broader psychosis have an increased risk of both non-violent and violent offending; this risk is greatest and most consistent for violent offences. Murray R, et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 541"},{"question":"All of the following factors are significantly associated with increased risk of violence among those with schizophrenia except","options":{"A":"Comorbid substance use","B":"Comorbid personality disorder","C":"Acute psychotic symptoms","D":"Non-compliance with treatment","E":"Comorbid depression"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The risk factors associated with violence in mental illness is a favourite topic in MRCPsych exams. It has been cogently shown that the magnitude of risk associated with a combination of factors such as male sex, young age, and lower socioeconomic status in a mentally ‘well’ person with no psychiatric history is higher than the risk of violence presented by mental disorders per se. Despite varied research, the causal pathway from mental illness to violence is still poorly sketched. The most consistently established risk factors that further increase the risk of violence among schizophrenia patients are (a) comorbid substance abuse, (b) comorbid personality disorder, (c) non-compliance with medication, and (d) active psychotic symptoms. Depression does not seem to be a major mediator of violence in schizophrenia patients. Walsh E, Buchanan A and Fahy T. Violence and schizophrenia: examining the evidence. British Journal of Psychiatry 2002; 180: 490–495. Murray R, et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 544"},{"question":"Which of the following is true about the epidemiology of violence in schizophrenia?","options":{"A":"Most offenders with schizophrenia offend for the first time after the onset of illness","B":"Most offenders with schizophrenia have delusions directly relevant to violence","C":"Most offenders with schizophrenia do not have substance use problems","D":"Most offenders with schizophrenia do not reoffend if the illness is diagnosed","E":"The risk factors increasing violence is similar in both schizophrenia and non-schizophrenia populations"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Most schizophrenia patients do not offend in direct response to delusions or hallucinations, although homicide offenders may be over-represented in those who are actively psychotic at the time of the offence. In general, schizophrenia patients who offend tend to have long histories of substance misuse, conduct problems, and delinquency, with extensive non-violent and violent offending prior to the onset of illness. Thus, the tendency to reoffend does not fall after a diagnosis of schizophrenia. The basic tenet one needs to remember regarding the epidemiology of violence in schizophrenia is that those risk factors for violence which operate in subjects without mental illness also operate in patients with schizophrenia. Murray R, et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 544"},{"question":"The amount of societal violence rate that can be ascribed to psychiatric illness is","options":{"A":"1 in 10","B":"1 in 20","C":"1 in 5","D":"1 in 2","E":"1 in 100"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Most research in forensic psychiatry has examined the relative risk of violence among the mentally ill compared with the general population. The population-attributable risk fraction (PAR%) refers to the percentage of violence in the population that can be ascribed to schizophrenia and thus could be eliminated if schizophrenia were eliminated from the population. Fazel and Grann (2006) reported that the population-attributable risk varied by gender and age in a given population. Overall, the PAR% of violence for psychiatric patients was 5.2%, suggesting that patients with severe mental illness commit 1 in 20 violent crimes. These data were obtained from analysing Swedish health registers between 1988 and 2000. This value may vary between countries and across various generations of birth cohorts. Fazel S and Grann M. The population impact of severe mental illness on violent crime. American Journal of Psychiatry 2006; 163: 1397–1403"},{"question":"With respect to population-attributable risk of violence in those with schizophrenia, which of the following is true?","options":{"A":"It is a more important public health measure than relative risk","B":"It increases with increasing overall crime rates","C":"Most crimes in Europe are committed by those with schizophrenia","D":"It decreases with increasing overall crime rates","E":"It represents the amount of crime that would remain if schizophrenia is completely eliminated from a population"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The population-attributable risk of violence in those with schizophrenia is a more important public health measure than relative risk as it indicates how much violence/crime could be eliminated if mental illness is ‘eliminated’. It provides an easier and more accurate reflection than relative risk for the general public. When the crime rates in a society increase, the population-attributable risk due to any mental illness reduces. The population-attributable risk fraction of violence for mental illness rate is estimated as 5% using Swedish registers; this suggests that most crimes in Europe are not related to mental illness. Murray R, et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 544"},{"question":"The term filicide refers to","options":{"A":"Killing of father by son","B":"Killing of a sister by another","C":"Killing of husband by wife","D":"Killing of a child by mother","E":"Killing of a parent by child"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The killing of a child by its mother is very rare and is called filicide. It is linked to depressive disorders more than any other mental illness. Patricide refers to the act of killing one’s father. Sororicide is the act of killing one’s sister. Matricide is the killing of one’s mother and mariticide is killing of one’s spouse. Fraternicide refers to killing one’s brother. Murray R, et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 545"},{"question":"To be applied successfully the fitness to plead criteria must be found relevant to a defendant at the time of","options":{"A":"The criminal offence","B":"The trial proceedings","C":"Being interviewed in custody","D":"Sentenced imprisonment","E":"The arrest"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The five criteria currently used in court in England and Wales to determine fitness to plead have remained unchanged for over 150 years. These are collectively termed Pritchard’s criteria: (1) ability to plead; (2) ability to understand evidence; (3) ability to understand the court proceedings; (4) ability to instruct a lawyer; (5) knowing that a juror can be challenged. As the degree of mental illness can vary with time, its effect on fitness to stand trial can differ. Hence it is important to establish fitness/unfitness in the defendant as applicable at the time of the trial proceedings. Rogers TP, Blackwood NJ, Farnham F., et al. Fitness to plead and competence to stand trial: a systematic review of the constructs and their application. Journal of Forensic Psychiatry and Psychology 2008; 19: 576–596"},{"question":"Which of the following refers to assessment of medical negligence?","options":{"A":"McNaughton’s criteria","B":"MacArthur’s competency assessment tool","C":"Pritchard’s criteria","D":"Hare’s checklist","E":"Bolam criteria"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"In the UK, the Bolam test has been the benchmark for assessing professional negligence since 1957. According to the Bolam test, ‘A doctor is not guilty of negligence if he has acted in accordance with a practice accepted as proper by a responsible body of medical men skilled in that particular art’. In other words, a doctor is not negligent if he is acting in accordance with such a practice, merely because there is a body of opinion that takes a contrary view. McNaughton’s test refers to the assessment of diminished responsibility in the wake of mental illness in court. The MacArthur competency assessment tool and Pritchard’s criteria are used for assessing fitness to plead. Hare’s checklist is used for the assessment of psychopathy. Jones JW. The healthcare professional and the Bolam test. British Dental Journal 2000; 188: 237–240"},{"question":"A ‘trial of facts’ takes place in which of the following conditions?","options":{"A":"Defendant is highly suggestible","B":"Defendant is unfit to plead","C":"Defendant has learning disability","D":"Defendant has amnesia for the event of crime","E":"Defendant is found not guilty by reason of insanity"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"If a defendant is found unfit to plead the likelihood of becoming fit is initially considered. If this is likely, e.g. following treatment, then the trial can be adjourned until such improvement occurs. If such improvement is unlikely, a jury trial of the facts takes place in the defendant’s absence to determine whether the individual committed the alleged crime. If the individual is unfit to plead but at the end of the trial of facts it is established that he/she has committed the act, then one or other form of court disposal (e.g. a hospital order, supervision order or absolute discharge) is given. Murray R, et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 557"},{"question":"Which of the following is a structured clinical risk assessment tool used in a forensic setting?","options":{"A":"Psychopathy Check List – Revised","B":"Violence Risk Appraisal Guide (VRAG)","C":"Iterative classification tree","D":"HCR-20","E":"Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory (MMPI)"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"HCR-20 (historical, clinical, risk management – 20) incorporates static historical risk factors, such as previous violence and early maladjustment, together with dynamic factors that may be particularly important in individual cases, such as level of insight and lack of personal support. It is a commonly used structured clinical risk assessment scale. VRAG is an actuarial tool that incorporates important predictors of reconviction studied in a sample of Canadian male offenders with mental disorder followed up for 7 years. PCL-R stands for the revised version of psychopathy checklist. It is used with HCR-20; it is not a stand-alone risk assessment instrument. MMPI is used as a psychometric tool for personality variables. The Iterative Classification Tree is an actuarial decision-making tool produced by Monahan et al. (2001) using data from the MacArthur risk assessment study. This tool uses many different combinations of bivariate risk factors to classify a person as high or low risk. Dolan M and Doyle M. Violence risk prediction. Clinical and actuarial measures and the role of the Psychopathy Checklist. British Journal of Psychiatry, 2000; 177: 303–311. Monahan J. and Silver E. Judicial decision thresholds for violence risk management. International Journal of Forensic Mental Health 2003; 2: 1–16"},{"question":"Which of the following is true with regard to VRAG?","options":{"A":"It incorporates HCR-20 as a subscale","B":"It contains 24 items","C":"Presence of schizophrenia is a predictor of lower risk","D":"Psychopathy is not included as a predictor","E":"It is a structured clinical risk assessment tool"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"VRAG is an actuarial risk tool that incorporates 12 items which are scored on the basis of a weighting procedure developed from the original study of Canadian prisoners. The variable with the heaviest weighting is the PCL-R psychopathy score, which is incorporated as a subscale. It does not use HCR-20 as a subscale. The factors positively associated with increased risk of recidivism are psychopathy score, history of elementary school difficulties, diagnosis of a personality disorder, young age, separation from parents prior to age 16, failure on prior conditional release, history of non-violent offences, never been married, and history of alcohol abuse. A diagnosis of schizophrenia is considered to reduce the overall risk of recidivism. Dolan M and Doyle M. Violence risk prediction. Clinical and actuarial measures and the role of the Psychopathy Checklist. British Journal of Psychiatry 2000; 177: 303–311"},{"question":"Which of the following is true with regard to the association between learning disability and offending?","options":{"A":"Above average IQ is an independent risk factor for offending","B":"Severity of learning disability correlates with severity of the offence","C":"Degree of learning disability correlates with rate of offending","D":"Homicide is the most common offence committed by those with a learning disability","E":"Substance abuse is associated with a risk of offending among the learning disabled"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Significantly below average intellectual ability is an independent predictor of future offending, irrespective of a diagnosis of learning disability (LD). Individuals with mild LD show a higher rate of offending than age- and sex-matched individuals without LD. No correlation has been found between the severity of intellectual disadvantage and the seriousness of the offence committed. In fact, individuals with more severe or profound learning disability rarely commit serious offences. Studies in the UK have shown a rate of 2–5% for recorded offences among the learning-disabled population. The degree of disability does not correlate with rate of offending. The most common offences by the learning-disabled group are property offences. Many risk factors that operate in the general population for risk of violence operate in the learning-disabled population, e.g. being young and male, a history of family offending, being unemployed, drug use, psychosocial disadvantage, etc. Riding B, Swann C and Swann B, eds. The Handbook of Forensic Learning Disabilities. Radcliffe Publishing 2005, p. 124"},{"question":"The proportion of male remand prisoners in England and Wales with at least one personality disorder is","options":{"A":"20%","B":"10%","C":"50%","D":"33%","E":"80%"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Almost 80% of male remand prisoners in England and Wales were found to have at least one personality disorder, with antisocial personality disorder being most prevalent. From the Office of National Statistics data (1997) the prevalence of any personality disorder was 78% for male remand prisoners, 64% for male sentenced prisoners and 50% for female prisoners (both sentenced and remand). Antisocial personality disorder had the highest prevalence of any category of personality disorder (63% of male remand prisoners, 49% of male sentenced prisoners, and 31% of female prisoners) followed by paranoid personality disorder in men (29% of male remand prisoners, 20% of male sentenced, and 16% of female prisoners) and borderline personality disorder in women (20% of female prisoners). Compare these rates with a weighted prevalence for any personality disorder of 4.4% among people aged 16–74 years in households in England, Scotland and Wales. Coid J, Yang M, Tyrer P et al. Prevalence and correlates of personality disorder in Great Britain. The British Journal of Psychiatry 2006; 188: 423–431. Singleton N, Meltzer, H., Gatward, R, et al. Psychiatric Morbidity among Prisoners in England and Wales. Stationery Office, 1998"},{"question":"The McNaughton rules are often discussed when a defence of insanity is used. Which of the following is NOT a factor that can be used for the insanity defence under the McNaughton rules?","options":{"A":"Disease of the mind","B":"Defect of reason","C":"Not knowing the nature and quality of the act","D":"Defect of moral judgement","E":"Absence of knowledge that the act is wrong"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The McNaughton rules refer to a set of guidelines for the insanity defence that was used in England until the 1960s. According to these rules one can plead the defence of insanity only if ‘at the time of committing the act, the accused was labouring under such a defect of reason from disease of the mind, as not to know the nature and quality of the act he was doing, or if he did know it then he did not know he was doing what was wrong’. Those who merely lack the capacity to control a criminal action could still be deemed punishable. Hence, a defect of moral judgement or failure to exercise existing capability to make the right decision cannot be brought up as an insanity defence under the McNaughton rules. Murray R, Kendler K, et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 558"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true with regard to the relationship between antisocial personality disorder and psychopathy?","options":{"A":"A minor subgroup of those with psychopathy have anti-social personality disorder","B":"All those with antisocial personality are psychopathic","C":"Only multiple homicide offenders can be classified as psychopathic","D":"Antisocial personality is a better predictor of violence risk than psychopathy","E":"Impulsive aggression is more common in those with antisocial personality without psychopathy"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The constructs of psychopathy and antisocial or dissocial personality are often referred to interchangeably, but in reality these are quite different concepts. Approximately 3–5% of people in the general population would meet the criteria for antisocial personality. But less than 1% will meet the criteria for psychopathy (i.e. a high score (30/40) on the PCL-R). Similarly, although only 15% of male prisoners have scores that fall in the psychopathy range on the PCL-R, nearly 80% of them will satisfy the criteria for antisocial personality disorder. In other words, although most patients (81%) diagnosed as psychopaths by the PCL-R criteria met the criteria for a diagnosis of antisocial personality disorder, only a minority (nearly 35–40%) of those with antisocial personality receive a diagnosis of PCL-R psychopathy. The correlation between antisocial personality disorder and PCL-R scores was much higher for behavioural (social deviance: r = 0.65) factor of psychopathy than affective (interpersonal: r = 0.39) factor. Psychopaths are less impulsively aggressive than those with antisocial personality disorder, but are more likely to engage in antisocial behaviour of an instrumental nature. Those with psychopathy commit higher rates of serious violence and have strikingly high rates of recidivism than those with antisocial personality disorder but who are not psychopathic. Ogloff JRP. Psychopathy/antisocial personality disorder conundrum. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry 2006; 40: 519–528. Murray R, Kendler K et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 547"},{"question":"Various neurobiological abnormalities have been documented in those with psychopathy. Which of the following is one such feature?","options":{"A":"Reduced fear-based learning","B":"Increased baseline autonomic arousal","C":"Reduced verbal IQ","D":"Increased reactive autonomic arousal on stimulation","E":"Increased P300 differentiation between target and non-target stimuli"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Various neurobiological findings have been demonstrated in those with psychopathy. These include impairments in appreciation of the emotional significance of external experience, strikingly low levels of baseline and reactive autonomic arousal and reduced fear-based learning. Although impaired verbal abilities have been demonstrated as a consistent risk factor for serious antisocial and delinquent behaviour, those with psychopathic traits often show serious antisocial behaviour, despite showing no impairment in their verbal abilities. In fact, Individuals who were high on callous–unemotional traits (a feature of psychopathy) with higher scores on the measure of verbal abilities reported the greatest violent delinquency in a sample of adolescent delinquents. For non-psychopathic individuals, a significant difference in P300 amplitude was noted between target and non-target stimuli. But in psychopathic individuals reliable P300 amplitude differences between the target and non-target visual conditions were not seen. Muñoz LC, Frick PJ, Kimonis ER, et al. Verbal ability and delinquency: testing the moderating role of psychopathic traits. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry 2008; 49: 414–421. Kiehl KA, Hare RD, Liddle PF, McDonald JJ. Reduced P300 responses in criminal psychopaths during a visual oddball task. Biological Psychiatry 1999; 45: 1498–1507"},{"question":"Which of the following is associated with a risk of aggression or violent behaviour in those without serious mental illness?","options":{"A":"Neurological soft signs","B":"Executive function deficits","C":"Minor physical anomalies","D":"Obstetric complications in pregnancy","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Even in those who are violent but do not have a demonstrable mental illness, the likelihood of having had a neurodevelopmental insult is high. This is shown by the presence of higher rates of minor physical anomalies in violently delinquent adolescents. Similarly, higher rates of neurological soft signs, maternal smoking during pregnancy, and obstetric complications have also been demonstrated. Defects in executive functioning and impulse control have also been shown to correlate with violence in the non-mentally ill samples. Murray R, Kendler K et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 549"},{"question":"In those who experience childhood maltreatment which of the following has been associated with a later risk of antisocial behaviour?","options":{"A":"Serotonin transporter polymorphism","B":"MAO enzyme polymorphism","C":"Dopamine receptor polymorphism","D":"COMT polymorphism","E":"Trinucleotide repeats in chromosome X"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Children differ in their response to maltreatment in terms of future risk of criminal behaviour. Although maltreatment increases the risk of later criminality by about 50%, most maltreated children do not become delinquents or adult criminals. It is possible that certain genetic susceptibility factors could influence the causal pathway. Caspi et al. demonstrated that the effect of childhood maltreatment on antisocial behaviour was significantly weaker among males with high MAO-A activity than among males with low MAO-A activity. It was also shown that girls with a low MAO-A activity genotype but not those with high MAO-A activity were more likely to develop conduct disorder if they were maltreated. Hence, high MAO-A activity has a protective influence against maltreatment for both sexes. Caspi A, McClay J, Moffitt TE, et al. Role of genotype in the cycle of violence in maltreated children. Science 2002; 297: 851–854"},{"question":"The most common group of mental disorders diagnosed among homicide offenders is","options":{"A":"Personality disorders","B":"Substance use disorders","C":"Schizophreniform disorders","D":"Affective disorders","E":"Learning disabilities"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Depending on the definitions used, the rates of ‘mental disorder’ vary greatly among homicide offenders. The national confidential inquiry into suicide and homicide by people with mental illness in the UK established the frequency of mental illness in a complete national sample of homicides as 44% (lifetime history of mental disorder). At the time of the homicide, 14% had symptoms of mental illness. The most frequent diagnosis was personality disorder (11%), closely followed by alcohol dependence (10%) and drug dependence. Among major mental illnesses, affective disorders (10%) were more common than schizophrenia (7%). Shaw J, Hunt IM, Flynn S, et al. Rates of mental disorder in people convicted of homicide. National clinical survey. British Journal of Psychiatry 2006; 188: 143–147"},{"question":"The proportion of those who commit homicide who are in contact with mental health services within the previous year is","options":{"A":"1–4%","B":"8–11%","C":"40–43%","D":"60–63%","E":"80–86%"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"From the national confidential inquiry on homicide (1996–9) data, only 8–11% of the total sample of all homicide offenders (n=1594) were in contact with mental health services at some time in the preceding year. The main diagnoses in those with any previous contact with mental health services were schizophrenia (24%), personality disorder (18%), and depressive disorder (16%). Psychiatric reports were not available for nearly one-quarter of all homicide cases. Shaw J, Hunt IM, Flynn S, et al. Rates of mental disorder in people convicted of homicide. National clinical survey. British Journal of Psychiatry 2006; 188: 143–147"},{"question":"Compared with homicide perpetrators who kill those who are known to them, perpetrators who kill strangers are more likely to","options":{"A":"Have a history of mental disorder","B":"Have a history of contact with mental health services","C":"Be a young female","D":"Have psychiatric symptoms at the time of offence","E":"Have a history of drug misuse"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The national confidential inquiry on homicide (1996–9) data found that 22% of all reported homicides were stranger homicides. In stranger homicides the perpetrator was more likely to be a young male and less likely to have a history of mental disorder or a history of contact with mental health services. They were also less likely to have psychiatric symptoms at the time of the offence than perpetrators of non-stranger homicides. They were more likely to have a history of drug or alcohol misuse. Shaw J, Amos T, Hunt IM, et al. Mental illness in people who kill strangers: longitudinal study and national clinical survey. British Medical Journal 2004; 328: 734–737"},{"question":"Which of the following is true with regard to men convicted of a sexual offence compared with men with no history of sexual offences in the general population?","options":{"A":"Sexual offenders have a similar risk for psychiatric hospitalization","B":"Sexual offenders have lower rates of schizophrenia","C":"Sexual offenders have higher rates of psychotic disorders","D":"Only organic psychiatric conditions are more prevalent among sexual offenders","E":"Sexual offenders have a reduced risk of bipolar disorder"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Traditional expert views on the association between sexual offending and psychiatric disorders were challenged by a case–control study using 13 years’ data from Swedish crime registers conducted by Fazel et al (2007). The authors compared sexual offenders with a random sample of men from the general population and reported that sexual offenders were more likely to have been hospitalized for a psychiatric condition than men in the general population (odds ratio (OR) 6.3). They also showed that sexual offenders were more likely to have a severe mental illness, including schizophrenia (OR 4.8), bipolar disorder (OR 3.4), other psychoses (OR 5.2), or an organic psychiatric condition (OR 2.4). Fazel S, Sjostedt G, Langstrom N, et al. Severe mental illness and risk of sexual offending in men: a case-control study based on Swedish national registers. Jornal of Clinical Psychiatry 2007; 68: 588–596"},{"question":"Elderly offenders are often an under-researched population compared with working age offenders. Which of the following is true regarding elderly sex offenders?","options":{"A":"Elderly sex offenders have higher rates of mental illness than non-sex offenders","B":"Elderly sex offenders have increased schizoid traits compared with non-sex offenders","C":"Sex offending in elderly people is associated more with organic brain disease","D":"Elderly sex offenders have increased antisocial traits compared with non-sex offenders","E":"There is an equal gender distribution among elderly sex offenders"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"As stated in the question, research is scarce in the area of criminality in elderly people. A case–control study comparing elderly sex offenders with elderly non-sex offenders showed that the rates of psychotic illness, depressive disorders, personality disorders, and dementia did not differ significantly between the two groups. Significant differences were observed at the level of personality traits wherein sex offenders were observed to have more schizoid, obsessive–compulsive, and avoidant traits but fewer antisocial traits than non-sex offenders. Similar to any other age group of sex offenders, the elderly group consisted exclusively of males. The authors concluded that sex offending in elderly people is associated more with personality factors than with mental illness or organic brain disease. Fazel S, Hope T, O’Donnell I and Jacoby R. Psychiatric, demographic and personality characteristics of elderly sex offenders. Psychological Medicine 2002; 32: 219–226"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true with respect to reduction in the risk of violence associated with schizophrenia?","options":{"A":"Newer antipsychotics reduce violence more than typical antipsychotics","B":"Violence risk is not modified by antipsychotic medications","C":"Medication adherence reduces risk of violence","D":"Olanzapine has the best evidence for reducing violence risk among atypical antipsychotics other than clozapine","E":"Typical antipsychotics increase the overall risk of violence"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The data from Clinical Antipsychotic Trials of Intervention Effectiveness (CATIE) project were analysed for the effect of antipsychotics on violent behaviour in those with schizophrenia. Violence declined from 16% to 9% in those who completed the antipsychotic treatment throughout the trial period of 6 months. But no demonstrable difference was found among the different medication groups; medication adherence was associated with a reduced risk of violence only in patients with no history of childhood antisocial conduct. Hence the effect of antipsychotics on violence in schizophrenia seems to depend on the effect of the drugs on acute psychopathology. This study did not show an advantage for second-generation antipsychotics in violence risk reduction when compared with first-generation antipsychotic perphenazine. Swanson JW, Swartz MS, Van Dorn RA, et al. Comparison of antipsychotic medication effects on reducing violence in people with schizophrenia. British Journal of Psychiatry 2008; 193: 37–43"},{"question":"The most important difference between legally determined non-insane automatisms and insane automatisms is","options":{"A":"Treatability","B":"Recurrence risk","C":"Presence of intent","D":"Degree of crime","E":"Impulsivity"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Automatism is a psychiatric defence used in cases of homicide. Under automatism, the defence counsel argues that the accused person’s behaviour at the time of the offence was ‘automatic’. In other words, mens rea was absent and the act was merely done without the conscious force of the mind – no intention was present. Some causes of automatism include hypoglycaemia, sleep walking, epilepsy, etc. In general, the defendant is acquitted if he/she is found to have a case of sane automatism, i.e. automatisms that occur due to external causes; these are unlikely to recur, hence the acquittal. Insane automatisms are due to ‘internal diseases’ or disorders of the mind, which have a propensity to recur. This classification is purely legal and not based on the impulsive nature of the crime or treatability of the condition. Note that both types of automatisms, by definition, mean that there is a lack of intent (mens rea). Often discrete medical disorders can be classified in either type of automatism. Murray R, Kendler K, et al., eds. Essential Psychiatry, 4th edn. Cambridge University Press, 2008, p. 558"},{"question":"With respect to morbid jealousy, the correct statement among the following is","options":{"A":"It is always a delusional disorder","B":"It is coded separately in ICD-10","C":"It is coded separately in DSM-IV","D":"It is classified as a paraphilia","E":"It is associated with amphetamine use"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Morbid jealousy (also known as Othello syndrome) may be a presenting feature of schizophrenia, delusional disorder, organic brain syndromes, or affective psychosis. It is not coded separately in ICD-10 or DSM-IV but as a subtype of delusional disorder; the delusion of infidelity is described by both systems of classification. Alcohol, amphetamine, or cocaine use can give rise to delusions of jealousy that may develop into full-blown delusional disorder in vulnerable individuals. Kingham M, Gordon H. Aspects of morbid jealousy. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2004; 10: 207–215"},{"question":"The most common relationship a victim may have with his/her stalker is","options":{"A":"Ex-partner","B":"Employer","C":"Medical practitioner","D":"Unrelated stranger","E":"Casual acquaintance"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Using a broad definition of stalking the British Crime Survey (2000) estimated that 2.9% of adults aged 16–59 had been stalked in the preceding year. Women (4.0%) were more likely to be victims of stalking/harassment than men (1.7%). Risks were particularly high for young women aged between 16 and 19 (16.8%). About a third of incidents were perpetrated by someone who was in an intimate relationship with the victim at the start of the episode or in the past. A community-based epidemiological study on stalking from a medium-sized German city reported that most of the stalking victims (32%) were pursued by former intimate partners. Budd T, Mattinson J. The extent and nature of stalking: findings from the 1998 British Crime Survey. Home Office; 2000. Dressing H, Kuehner C, Gass P. Lifetime prevalence and impact of stalking in a European population. British Journal of Psychiatry 2005; 187: 168–172"},{"question":"Which of the following ICD-10 diagnoses has a well-demonstrated causal association leading to stalking behaviour?","options":{"A":"Obsessive–compulsive disorder","B":"Delusional disorder","C":"Depressive disorder","D":"Organic brain disorders","E":"Pervasive developmental disorder"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Delusional disorder or erotomanic type has a well-known link with stalking behaviour. An often-cited descriptive study of stalking was carried out by Mullen et al. (1999) in a group of 145 stalkers referred to a psychiatric centre. Mullen grouped stalkers into rejected, intimacy-seeking, incompetent, resentful, and predatory types. These are arbitrary and not entirely exclusive groupings, although such typology helps in predicting the likely nature and duration of stalking and the risk of assault to a certain extent. Among these, the rejected stalkers make up the largest group, formed predominantly of ex-partners. The predatory stalkers form a small group with a high potential for sexual violence. Mullen described incompetent stalkers as ‘intellectually limited and socially incompetent individuals with rudimentary courting rituals’ whose victims do not reciprocate their affection. Resentful stalkers tend to frighten and distress the victim because of a sense of grievance. The intimacy-seeking stalkers form a spectrum, from those with erotomania to those with rigid infatuations. The erotomanic delusions could be both secondary to pre-existing psychotic disorders such as schizophrenia and as part of a delusional disorder. Mullen PE, Pathé M, Purcell R, Stuart GW. Study of stalkers. American Journal of Psychiatry 1999; 156: 1244–1249"},{"question":"It is found that criminal parents are at higher risk of having delinquent children. Which of the following is a correct statement in this regard?","options":{"A":"Most criminal parents directly encourage crime in their children","B":"Most criminal parents do not mind if their children commit a criminal offence","C":"Findings of genetic transmission in delinquency have been shown to be robust","D":"Poor parental supervision from criminal parents increases delinquency rates","E":"Parents and children get convicted for the same crime more often than not"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"It is well established that having a convicted mother, father, brother, or sister significantly predicts juvenile delinquency in boys. Thus intergenerational continuity in offending has been noted. There is no evidence that criminal parents directly encourage their children to commit crime; in fact, most convicted men disagreed with the statement that ‘I would not mind if my son/daughter committed a criminal offence’. Epidemiological studies have shown that it was extremely rare for a parent and a child to be convicted for an offence committed together. Thus, the major mediator between parental criminality and juvenile delinquency seems to be poor parental supervision, with some role for genetic transmission of antisocial behaviour. Farrington, D.P. (1995). The development of offending and antisocial behaviour from childhood: key findings from the Cambridge Study in Delinquent Development. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, 36, 929–64"},{"question":"All of the following features are supportive of violence occurring during epileptic automatism except","options":{"A":"Violent behaviour provoked by the victim","B":"Presence of impaired consciousness","C":"Poorly directed behaviour","D":"Stereotyped motor acts preceding violent behaviour","E":"Evidence of amnesia for the behaviour"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Violent acts during epilepsy are extremely uncommon. But epileptic automatisms have been invoked as a defence in courts time and again. Most cases involved spontaneous, non-directed, stereotyped aggressive movements, with violence against property being more common than inflicting serious bodily injuries. Severe violence, if seen at all, is largely restricted to postictal states. When aggression presents as a feature of an epileptic seizure, it usually begins suddenly without provocation, lasts only for brief periods, and ends abruptly with evidence of impaired consciousness during the act. The act usually does not involve detailed or interactive behaviour but appears stereotyped. Episodes of postictal or ictal violence are usually associated with amnesia for the event. Marsh L, Krauss GL. Aggression and violence in patients with epilepsy. Epilepsy and Behavior 2000; 1: 160–168"},{"question":"An offender with a history of repeated arson admits to deliberate fire-setting, which is preceded by a certain degree of arousal. He has had a fascination with fire since childhood and achieves a sense of gratification when setting fires. He does not have antisocial personality disorder or substance use. The most appropriate diagnosis is","options":{"A":"Obsessive compulsive disorder","B":"Pyromania","C":"Intellectual disability","D":"Intermittent explosive disorder","E":"Sadistic personality disorder"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Pyromania is an extremely rare disorder that presents with repeated fire-setting. It is recognized as a category in both ICD-10 and DSM-IV, under impulse control disorders. The diagnostic criteria include tension or affective arousal before the act of setting the fire, fascination with, interest in, curiosity about, or attraction to fire and its situational contexts, as well as pleasure, gratification, or relief when setting fires or when witnessing or participating in the aftermath of a fire. Lindberg N, Holi M, Tani P, Virkkunen M. Looking for pyromania: characteristics of a consecutive sample of Finnish male criminals with histories of recidivist fire-setting between 1973 and 1993. BMC Psychiatry 2005; 5: 47"},{"question":"During the proceedings of a court trial it becomes evident that a murder victim had the habit of achieving sexual excitement from being humiliated and beaten after being bound and verbally abused. This is consistent with","options":{"A":"Voyeurism","B":"Sadism","C":"Masochism","D":"Fetishism","E":"Hypoxyphilia"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Masochism refers to a paraphilia characterized by persistent interest in sexual activities that demean, humiliate, or cause suffering to self. Masochism requires a partner who complies by dominating and inflicting suffering. In contrast, sadism refers to a paraphilia wherein sexual arousal and gratification are obtained by inflicting pain and suffering upon the partner. Hence a sadist and a masochist can be mutual partners. Voyeurism is characterized by achieving gratification by watching people undressing or having sexual intercourse. It is the most common paraphilia reported. Fetishism refers to compulsive sexual interest in inanimate objects that are often worn by or associated with sexual partners. Hypoxyphilia (autoerotic asphyxiation) is not separately coded as a paraphilia in ICD/DSM; it refers to a specific form of masochism in which sexual arousal is attained by self-suffocation, e.g. via hanging while masturbating. Millon T, Blaney PH, Davis RD, eds. Oxford Textbook of Psychopathology. Oxford University Press, 1999, p. 422"},{"question":"In people with kleptomania which of the following medications has been demonstrated to be the most useful in double-blinded randomized controlled trials?","options":{"A":"Fluoxetine","B":"Olanzapine","C":"Lithium","D":"Naloxone","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Kleptomania is considered by some as part of the obsessive–compulsive spectrum. Extending the effectiveness of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRI) in obsessive compulsive spectrum disorders, several case series of successful SSRI use in kleptomania have appeared. A response rate of nearly 80% at week 7 was reported for kleptomania in an open-label trial of escitalopram; this was not maintained to the same degree in a subsequent double-blind placebo-controlled discontinuation trial. Naltrexone and mood stabilizers have also been studied in open-label trials for kleptomania, with variable benefits. To date, no strong evidence from randomized controlled trials exists to support pharmacological interventions in kleptomania. Koran LM, Aboujaoude EN, Gamel NN. Escitalopram treatment of kleptomania: an open-label trial followed by double-blind discontinuation. Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 2007; 68: 422–427"},{"question":"The proportion of adults with a history of childhood conduct disorder who satisfy the criteria for antisocial personality disorder in cross-sectional interviews is","options":{"A":"75%","B":"10%","C":"20%","D":"3%","E":"95%"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Traditionally it was thought that 40% of those with conduct disorder experience lifetime persistence of traits that are termed as antisocial personality disorder. But this has been now challenged to be an underestimate; data from the National Epidemiologic Survey on Alcohol and Related Conditions (NESARC) in the USA suggests that nearly 75% of adults who were retrospectively identified to have had conduct disorder as children satisfied current criteria for antisocial personality disorder. Although this is a retrospective design, the estimates are from a more representative sample than older retrospective studies. Gelhorn HL, Sakai JT, Price RK, Crowley TJ. DSM-IV conduct disorder criteria as predictors of antisocial personality disorder. Comprehensive Psychiatry 2007; 48: 529–538"},{"question":"Among all homicides committed by those with psychotic illnesses, the proportion committed by those with a first episode psychosis and receiving no treatment is","options":{"A":"1 in 10","B":"2 in 10","C":"4 in 10","D":"7 in 10","E":"9 in 10"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The prevalence of schizophrenic disorders in the general population is below 1%, but patients with schizophrenia constitute between 5% and 20% of all homicide offenders. An increased risk of homicide has been associated with the first episode of psychosis. A meta-analysis of studies reporting homicide offences in psychotic patients showed that 38.5% of homicides occurred during the first episode of psychosis, prior to initial treatment. The rate ratio of homicide in the first episode of psychosis was 15.5 times the annual rate of homicide after treatment for psychosis. Nearly 40% of patients with schizophrenia who commit homicides do not have any history of psychiatric care. Nielssen O, Large M. Rates of homicide during the first episode of psychosis and after treatment: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Schizophrenia Bulletin 2008; doi:10.1093/schbul/sbn144"},{"question":"Among various mental disorders seen in shoplifters, the strongest association is seen for","options":{"A":"Borderline personality disorder","B":"Antisocial personality disorder","C":"Schizophrenia","D":"Depression","E":"Kleptomania"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Shoplifting is different from kleptomania: the former is a broadly defined behaviour whereas the latter is a specific psychiatric diagnostic category. Data from a national study carried out in the USA (National Epidemiologic Survey on Alcohol and Related Conditions) have demonstrated that most individuals (nearly 90%) who admitted to at least one episode of lifetime shoplifting had a lifetime history of at least one psychiatric diagnosis, compared with nearly 50% in non-shoplifters. In both groups, the most prevalent disorders were nicotine dependence and alcohol use disorders, with nearly three or four times increased risk respectively; among shoplifters, the strongest associations were found for antisocial personality disorder and substance use disorders. Kleptomania is a rare condition and occurs in less than 5% of identified shoplifters and less than 0.6% of the general population. Blanco C, Grant J, Petry NM, et al. Prevalence and correlates of shoplifting in the united states: results from the national epidemiologic survey on alcohol and related conditions (NESARC). American Journal of Psychiatry 2008; 165: 905–913"},{"question":"A 43-year-old patient with a diagnosis of delusional disorder reveals that he intends to ‘rip off’ his neighbour, with whom he believes that his wife is having an affair. Which of the following is correct with regard to management of this patient?","options":{"A":"Police must not be informed to preserve confidentiality; wife can be informed","B":"Wife must not be informed to preserve confidentiality; police must be informed","C":"Police, wife, and, if needed, the neighbour must be informed","D":"Only the neighbour must be informed as there are no thoughts to harm the wife","E":"No one needs to be informed if the patient is legally detained in a hospital"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"In Tarasoff v The Regents of the University of California et al., a case was brought by the parents of Tatiana Tarasoff, who had been murdered by Prosenjit Poddar. Poddar had previously disclosed his violent feelings against Tarasoff to Dr Moore, the campus psychologist. Although Dr Moore notified the police of his concerns about Poddar, the police released him after questioning. Ms Tarasoff and her family were not warned of the danger she faced. The court ruled that the clinician had a duty to protect and warn a third party from risk of harm from his/her patient, even though that third party was not under the clinician’s clinical care. In the UK, a Tarasoff ruling does not apply directly; breach of confidentiality for the sake of public interest has been recognized. According to Tarasoff principles, the police and third parties must be warned of the risk as well as the wife"},{"question":"The proportion of prisoners in English prisons with one or other diagnosable mental disorder is","options":{"A":"30%","B":"15%","C":"45%","D":"90%","E":"5%"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Data from Psychiatric Morbidity among Prisoners in England and Wales 1998 showed that a large proportion of all prisoners had several mental disorders. Only 1 in 10 or fewer showed no evidence of any of the five disorders considered in the survey (personality disorder, psychosis, neurosis, alcohol misuse, and drug dependence). Thus the rate of psychiatric diagnosis was nearly 90% in prisons. Most prisoners who had a psychiatric diagnosis had more than one diagnosable condition; this was especially true if the primary diagnosis was psychotic illness. Rates for multiple disorders were higher among remand than sentenced prisoners. Despite this, most prisoners receive poor, if any, psychiatric services in prison. Singleton N, Meltzer H, Gatward R, et al Psychiatric Morbidity among Prisoners in England and Wales. Stationery Office, 1998"},{"question":"All of the following are true with regard to suicide of a homicide perpetrator except","options":{"A":"The suicide usually occurs within a week of murder","B":"It most commonly follows domestic homicides","C":"It follows child homicides more often than adult homicides","D":"It is most commonly associated with bipolar disorder","E":"An altruistic motive may be seen in elderly people"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Homicide–suicides are mostly family affairs, especially when the perpetrator is female. Barraclough and Harris (2002) studied all murder–suicides over a 4-year period in the UK and found that 3% of male, 11% of female, and 19% of child homicides were of this type. Similarly, of all suicides, 0.8% male and 0.4% female deaths occurred as homicide–suicides. The typical cases involved families of low socioeconomic status. Death or fatal injury occurred on the same day in nearly 90% of incidents; in atypical cases the maximum interval between suicide and homicide was 10 months. In elderly people such homicide–suicide combinations are often suicide pacts complicated by depression or dementia in a couple or one of the partners. They can be considered altruistic, as often elderly people believe that the world will be better off without them"},{"question":"In UK prisons, the most common method of committing suicide is","options":{"A":"Hanging","B":"Poisoning","C":"Jumping from a height","D":"Gunshot injuries","E":"Self-immolation"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"A 2-year national survey of prison suicides described the clinical and social circumstances of self-inflicted deaths among prisoners in England and Wales. Nearly one-third occurred within 7 days of arrival in prison. The commonest method (nearly 92%) was hanging or self-strangulation; nearly three-quarters had a history of mental disorder. The commonest primary diagnosis was drug dependence"},{"question":"In which of the following settings are anatomical dolls used to aid interview?","options":{"A":"Interviewing a learning-disabled adult for criminal offence","B":"Interviewing a child for diagnosing conduct disorder","C":"Interviewing an adult perpetrator of child abuse","D":"Interviewing a child for the possibility of sexual abuse","E":"Interviewing a child with suspected gender identity disorder"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Anatomical dolls are used in forensic investigation of children who are alleged victims of sexual abuse. Various procedures such as drawings, puppets, observation for sexualized behaviour, etc., have been used to obtain a child’s report of sexual abuse. But research has not confirmed that responses supposedly indicative of abuse (e.g. drawing genitalia in human figure drawings, demonstrating intercourse, or oral sex between anatomical dolls, etc.) consistently occur with high frequency among abused children. Hence the use of such methods is controversial"},{"question":"A patient with chronic schizophrenia has improved core signs and symptoms. His remaining symptoms are of such low intensity that they no longer interfere significantly with his behaviour. The burden of current symptoms is such that if assessed now using standard criteria, he would not be diagnosed as having schizophrenia, although his social and vocational functioning has not altered much over the course of treatment. Which of the following correctly describes this state?","options":{"A":"Recovery","B":"Remission","C":"Deficit state","D":"Lucid interval","E":"Recrudescence"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The Remission in Schizophrenia Working Group defined remission ‘as a state in which patients have experienced improvements in core signs and symptoms to the extent that any remaining symptoms are of such low intensity that they no longer interfere significantly with behaviour and are below the threshold typically utilized in justifying an initial diagnosis of schizophrenia’. Thus ‘remission’ is not the same as ‘recovery’, which is the ability to function in the community, socially and vocationally, as well as being relatively free of psychopathology. Accordingly, remission is a necessary but not sufficient step towards recovery. Note that such a scientific definition of recovery views recovery as a state of outcome; this is very different from the concept of recovery promulgated by consumer groups"},{"question":"While measuring non-adherence to psychotropic medications, which of the following groups provides a subjective overestimate of the true adherence rates?","options":{"A":"Patient group","B":"Doctors treating the patients","C":"Pharmacist","D":"Both A and B","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"In clinical practice, medication adherence is either assumed de facto or assessed from patients’ self-reports. Both these measures of adherence have limited validity. Medication levels in body fluids are susceptible to manipulation. The use of electronic monitoring and a third party such as a pharmacist/clinical assistant to assess adherence may be more useful. Using the measurement of adherence as a dichotomous variable, a study comparing adherence estimates by patients, clinicians, and research assistants using electronic monitors was carried out. Compared with electronic monitoring, prescribers dramatically overestimated adherence levels. Electronic monitoring detected greater non-adherence rates (57%) than either prescribers (7%) or patients (5%), although independent third-party ratings were closer to electronic ratings (54%)"},{"question":"According to the European schizophrenia cohort study, homelessness experienced by patients with schizophrenia is highest in","options":{"A":"Germany","B":"France","C":"Great Britain","D":"Belgium","E":"Turkey"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Homelessness has a recognized association with severe mental illness. ‘Rooflessness’ refers to those living on the streets; it is difficult to include them in research surveys. Hence most researchers use a looser definition of having no fixed address and include people living in hostels and emergency accommodation. A broader term of ‘housing instability’ refers to the tenuousness of housing tenure. In the USA, community studies show that about a fifth of those with schizophrenia had no fixed address – a rate that was 2.4 times higher than for major depression"},{"question":"Which of the following is the major principle behind the original development of assertive community treatment?","options":{"A":"Transfer of learnt social skills from the hospital to community setting is difficult","B":"Social skills training in the hospital setting is costly","C":"Training in community living is not a necessary component of rehabilitation","D":"Vocational rehabilitation can only take place in the community","E":"Cost of inpatient management is higher than the cost of community management"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Assertive community treatment (ACT) was initially developed from the ‘training in community living’ programme at the Mendota Mental Health Institute in Madison, Wisconsin, by Marx, Stein, and Test. According to them community rehabilitation existent in the 1970s served only to maintain patients in ‘a tenuous community adjustment on the brink of rehospitalization’, instead of helping patients to meet all their needs. The key principle was to provide treatment in community settings, because skills learnt in the community can be better applied in the community"},{"question":"Subjective measures of quality of life (QOL) in patients with mental illness may be inaccurate because of","options":{"A":"QOL scales always include depression and anxiety items","B":"Reduced expectations may lead to claims of good QOL","C":"QOL is not measurable using questionnaires","D":"Subjective measures of QOL are not standardized","E":"Response rate for subjective QOL measures is very low"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"QOL is measurable using questionnaires; these measures can be subjective or objective and many standardized instruments for both are available. Most but not all QOL instruments contain ‘emotional’ items, mostly relating to depression and anxiety. Such scales when applied to psychiatric conditions become tautological as the content of both measures largely overlap, e.g. the Quality of Life in Depression Scale (QLDS), which is made up mainly of depressive symptoms. Subjective measures of QOL in psychiatry are particularly problematic because of ‘affective, cognitive or reality distortion fallacies’. A depressed patient may underestimate his true QOL; similarly, psychopathological states may lead to distorted appraisal of one’s QOL. Hence external (e.g. relatives/carers) appraisal may be necessary to complement subjective QOLs in psychiatry"},{"question":"Which of the following projects refers to promoting spontaneous recovery in schizophrenia without compulsory use of psychotropics?","options":{"A":"Henderson hospital project","B":"Soteria project","C":"Partial hospitalization project","D":"Utopia project","E":"Melbourne PACE project"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Different models of therapeutic communities have been tried as alternatives to hospitalization for people diagnosed with schizophrenia. Some of these models emphasized the need for individuals to experience psychosis with minimal interference and high levels of support instead of early intervention with antipsychotic medication"},{"question":"According to the health belief model of treatment compliance, patients consider all of the following factors when deciding upon treatment adherence except","options":{"A":"Susceptibility to illness","B":"Severity of illness","C":"Perceived benefits","D":"Probability of side-effects","E":"Social criticism"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"According to the health belief model four main belief categories have an impact on patients’ compliance with prescribed treatment. These are (1) perceived benefits, (2) perceived costs, (3) perceived susceptibility to illness and cure, (4) secondary benefits of medication and adherence. This model emphasizes the patient’s decision-making process, which is composed of a subjective cost–benefit analysis in the context of the patient’s personal goals and priorities"},{"question":"The vocational rehabilitation programme with best evidence in schizophrenia is","options":{"A":"Sheltered employment model","B":"Supported employment model","C":"Clubhouse model","D":"Skills training model","E":"Token economy model"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Competitive employment rates are low in schizophrenia. People with mental health disorders represent the largest group (40%) who claim incapacity benefit. Various vocational programmes have been tried and tested in schizophrenia rehabilitation. Work acts as both a process and the outcome for rehabilitation in chronic schizophrenia"},{"question":"The proportion of patients of working age with serious mental health problems who are employed actively in the UK is","options":{"A":"10%","B":"50%","C":"40%","D":"75%","E":"1%"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Annual (now quarterly) labour force surveys in the UK yield the rates of employment for the mentally ill population. Patients with a significant mental illness are among the most excluded in society. It is estimated that, at best, 15% of working age people with long-term mental health problems are working, far lower than any other group of disabled people"}]');export{e as default};
